Finding Aid for Talbot Smith papers, 1918-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Talbot Smith papers 1918-1978
Smith, Talbot.
46.3 linear feet
87240 Aa 2
Lawyer, teacher, jurist, justice of the Michigan Supreme Court, the U.S. District Court for the Eastern District of Michigan, and the U.S. Court of Appeals. Correspondence, speeches, case files, and research materials; also photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Talbot Smith, Jr. (donor no. 4685 ) on January 15, 1987.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Talbot Smith was born October 11, 1899 in Fayette, Missouri. His father, an Episcopal minister, moved the family a great deal throughout the midwestern and western areas of the United States during Talbot's younger years, and hence he attended a number of grammar and high schools before graduating in Wyoming in 1917. He entered the United States Naval Academy the same year, and while at Annapolis he received a Bachelor of Science degree in engineering in 1920. He married Lola Hamlen the following year. While still in the Navy Smith also attended the University of Michigan and earned a Master of Science degree in chemical engineering in 1927.
Smith retired from active duty in the Navy on January 1, 1931 as a lieutenant, senior grade. He then went to work as an engineer for Atlantic Refining Company in Philadelphia, where he served as a trouble-shooter for customers' problems with the company's fuel oil and equipment. This type of work did not appeal to him, however, and so he worked at Atlantic Refining long enough only to save money to enable him to enter into the profession which really appealed to him - law. He applied at several different law schools and was rejected; one of these, the University of California, fifteen years later accepted Smith as a faculty member in its law school. Many of the law school deans were convinced that the combination of Smith's age -- thirty-two at the time of his application - along with his "military mind" would prove a barrier too formidable to be overcome in the pursuit of a law degree. Nevertheless, Smith persisted and was accepted at the University of Michigan for the fall semester in 1931. "The Admiral," as he was known by his classmates, both in deference to his age as well as his naval background, graduated with a J.D. degree in February, 1934. Immediately afterwards Smith joined the Detroit law firm of Monaghan, Crowley, Reilley and Kellog. This firm specialized in corporate law, and after several years Smith was given a small percentage of the firm's profits in addition to his regular salary, though he never became a partner in this firm.
In the fall of 1937 Smith went to the University of Missouri, where he taught courses in corporations and contracts. He remained on the faculty there until 1941, when he left to take a position with the U.S. Office of Price Administration. He worked with others in helping to draft the Price Control Act, and later served as chief of both the Appellate and Briefing Section and the Civil Litigation Section. In these positions Smith spent much time in court trying to establish the constitutionality of the federal government's price and rent control policies. Once this was done Smith became a regional O.P.A. attorney in Texas. His jurisdiction there was quite large, covering the states of Texas, Oklahoma, Louisiana, Missouri, and Kansas.
Smith returned to Ann Arbor in 1944 where he joined the law firm of Burke and Burke, later to be Burke, Burke and Smith. There he handled mostly general practice, though he did do much counseling with the Regents of the University of Michigan. In 1945 Smith accepted an offer from the University of California at Berkley to again teach corporate law and contracts courses. Financial compensation, however, was much less in university teaching than in private practice, and so Smith resigned after one year, 1946-1947, and returned again to his private practice in Ann Arbor.
While in private practice Smith became involved in Michigan State government and Democratic politics. He served as a member of the Michigan Anti-subversive Legislative Study Commission in 1951, the Board of Inquiry into the Southern Michigan Prison Riot in Jackson in 1952 and also on the Michigan Corrections Committee.
In 1953, Smith ran for office as a Michigan Supreme Court Justice but lost by a large margin. He remained active in Michigan Democratic Party politics following this defeat, and was appointed to the Michigan Supreme Court by Governor G. Mennen Williams in 1955, succeeding George E. Bushnell. He successfully ran for election in November 195 for the term ending in December 1957, and then was reelected for a full eight-year term.
While a member of the Michigan Supreme Court, Talbot Smith gained both a nickname and a reputation as "the great dissenter." During his first sixteen months as a member of the court he wrote fifteen dissenting opinions. Smith's dissenting opinions won him great praise from many, especially from the Dean of Harvard Law School Roscoe Pound. His successful 1957 reelection campaign was built largely upon his reputation as a dissenter.
Macmillan Publishing Company approached Smith while he was a member of the Michigan Supreme Court and asked him to consider authorship of a book on the legal profession in a series on career choices for college graduates. Smith initially declined the offer to prepare the monograph on law, but later accepted. His book Lawyer, was published in March 1961.
In October 1961 Smith was appointed by President Kennedy to be a Justice for the United States District Court for the Eastern District of Michigan. The appointment was confirmed, and he assumed his duties as a federal district judge in 1962. Smith served in this capacity for ten years before assuming senior status in October 1971. After this he continued to sit by designation on various Courts of Appeals, particularly in St. Louis. And though he reduced his case load a great deal by this time, Smith continued to write opinions with some frequency. Talbot Smith passed away in December 1978 at the age of 79.
The papers of Talbot Smith have been divided into the following series: Personal and early career material, Judicial career, Case files and related, Research and topical Files, and Other materials.
Subjects:
Judges--Michigan.; Law.; Michigan. Supreme Court.; Smith, Talbot.; United States. District Court (Michigan: Eastern District); United States. Navy.; United States. Office of Price Administration.; University of Missouri.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Judges--Michigan.; Michigan. Supreme Court.; Smith, Talbot.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Smith, Talbot.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Edwards, George, 1914-; Hart, Philip A. (Philip Aloysius), 1912-1976.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Personal and early career 1918-1955
  The Personal and early career series covers the period of 1918 to 1955. This series includes biographical information, a diary kept while in the US Navy, class notes and other material from courses taken at the University of Michigan Law School, case notes and correspondence from his work with Monaghan, Crowley, Reilley and Kellog, materials from his years teaching at the University of Missouri, and correspondence from his service with the Office of Price Administration and his work with Burke, Burke and Smith.
  - Biographical (Box 1)
  - Navy 1918-1930
    - Diary 1918 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1920-1930, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Thesis 1927 (U-M chemical engineering) (Box 1)
  - Atlantic Refining,: "An Atlantic Interlude," 1931, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Law School 1931-1932
    - Case notes undated, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Class notes undated (Box 1)
    - Class notebook 1931 (Box 1)
    - Class notes Aigler's Lectures on Titles 1931-1932, 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - Durfee's Lectures on Equity 1932, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - Monaghan, Crowley, Reilley and Kellog 1934-1937
    - Case notes
      - Undated (Box 1)
      - Creditor's rights undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1936 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1934-1937 (Box 1)
  - University of Missouri 1937-1941
    - Correspondence and memoranda 1937-1941, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Final exams and marks 1937-1941, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Classwork 1938-1939, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Scope of the Business 1940, 1 volumes (Box 2)
    - Collateral Negligence 1941, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Corporation Finance undated, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - Office of Price Administration 1941-1944
    - Correspondence
      - 1941, 1942, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - 1943, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - 1944 (Box 2)
  - Burke, Burke and Smith 1944-1955
    - Correspondence
      - 1944-1947 (Box 2)
      - 1948 (Box 2)
      - 1949-1951 (Box 2)
      - 1952 (Box 2)
      - 1953, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - 1954-1955, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - University of California 1947
    - Supplemental cases and materials with list of assignments 1947 (Box 3)
- Judicial Career 1955-1978
  The Judicial Career series relates to both his years with the Michigan Supreme Court, the United States District Court, and the United States Court of Appeals. The Michigan Supreme Court subseries contains correspondence, undated memoranda, material relating to the proposed Missouri plan, and several months of Smith's schedule during 1956 and 1957. The United States District Court subseries contains a book review, case notes, and correspondence. The United States Court of Appeals subseries is made up of correspondence 1971 to 1977. An important part of the Judicial Career series are the various speeches written by Smith, some delivered and some not, during the period 1956 to 1974.
  - Michigan Supreme Court 1955-1961
    - Correspondence
      - 1955 (Box 3)
      - 1956, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1957, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1958, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - 1959, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - 1960, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1961 (Box 3)
    - Memoranda undated (Box 3)
    - Missouri Plan 1955 (Box 3)
    - Schedule
      - January-July 1956 (Box 3)
      - March 1957 (Box 3)
  - United States District Court 1961-1971
    - Book review 1962 (Box 3)
    - Case notes undated
      - Borrowed servants (Box 3)
      - Contracts fraud, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Ratification (Box 3)
      - Undisclosed principal (Box 3)
      - Termination of agency (Box 3)
      - Corporations (Box 3)
      - Partnerships (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1961-1971
      - A-E, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - F-K, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - L-R, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - S-Z, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - United States Court of Appeals 1971-1977
    - Correspondence 1971-1977 (Box 4)
  - Speeches 1956-1974, undated
    - Layman's League March 27, 1956 (Box 4)
    - Frank Murphy Memorial Dedication May 1960 (Box 4)
    - National Conference of Bar Examiners 1960 (Box 4)
    - Phi Beta Kappa May 8, 1962 (Box 4)
    - Queen's University June 5, 1962 (Box 4)
    - St. Louis September 9-10, 1964 (Box 4)
    - University of Alabama April 19, 1969 (Box 4)
    - New York Practicing Law Institute October 31, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous 1973-1974, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Fort Shelby undated (Box 4)
    - Law Day undated (Box 4)
- Case files and related
  The Case files and related series is made up of appellate and civil cases. The Appellate cases are arranged chronologically and span the dates September 1972 to April 1978. The Civil Cases, measuring eight linear feet, are arranged by case number, and cover various dates.
  - Appellate Cases 1972-1978
    - September-October 1972 (Box 5)
    - October 1972-April 1973 (Box 6)
    - May-September 1973 (Box 7)
    - October-December 1973 and correspondence, November 1972-December 1978 (Box 8)
    - January-May 1974 (Box 9)
    - July-August 1974 (Box 10)
    - September 1974 (Box 11)
    - November 1974-February 1975 (Box 12)
    - March 1975 (Box 13)
    - May-September 1975 (Box 14)
    - March-May 1976 (Box 15)
    - September-November 1976 (Box 16)
    - February-November 1977 (Box 17)
    - January-April 1978 (Box 18)
  - Civil Cases
    - Nos. 19,000-25,283 (Box 19)
    - Nos. 25,283-25,979 (Box 20)
    - Nos. 26,189-29,094 (Box 21)
    - Nos. 29,094-30,587 (Box 22)
    - Nos. 30,605-33,750 (Box 23)
    - Nos. 34,000-37-026 (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous and Michigan Supreme Court (Box 25)
    - Miscellaneous and Michigan Supreme Court (Box 26)
- Research and Topical files
  The Research and Topical Files series documents Smith's continuing interest and study of the law and legal issues.
  - Miscellaneous
    - A-Con, 4 volumes (Box 27)
    - D-Fha, 6 volumes (Box 28)
    - G-I, 5 volumes (Box 29)
    - J-O, 5 volumes (Box 30)
    - P-S, 5 volumes (Box 31)
    - W-Z and miscellaneous, 7 volumes (Box 32)
  - December 1963-January 1964, 4 volumes (Box 33)
  - Alphabetical I
    - Admiralty, 1 volumes (Box 33)
    - Ann Arbor High School, 1 volumes (Box 33)
    - Appellate Slip Opinions 1974-1978, 1 volumes (Box 34)
    - Arraignments, 1 volumes (Box 34)
    - Assault, 1 volumes (Box 34)
    - Bank Case, 1 volumes (Box 34)
    - Bench Book, 1 volumes (Box 34)
    - Briefing Books, 4 volumes (Box 34)
    - Case Service (Products Liability), 1 volumes (Box 35)
    - Civil Rights, 2 volumes (Box 35)
    - Confessions and Identifications, 1 volumes (Box 35)
    - Conspiracy, 2 volumes (Box 35)
    - Contracts, 1 volumes (Box 35)
    - Criminal Justice Act, 1 volumes (Box 36)
    - Criminal Matters, 1 volumes (Box 36)
    - Criminal Procedures, 1 volumes (Box 36)
    - Datebook, 1 volumes (Box 36)
    - Dearborn Seminar, 2 volumes (Box 36)
    - Dearborn Seminar, 2 volumes (Box 37)
    - Desk Book for Sentencing, 1 volumes (Box 37)
    - Diversity, 1 volumes (Box 37)
    - Evidence, 2 volumes (Box 37)
    - Extradition, 1 volumes (Box 37)
    - Grand Jury, 1 volumes (Box 37)
    - Hearsay, 1 volumes (Box 38)
    - Injunctions Against State, 1 volumes (Box 38)
    - Joint Sentencing Institute, 1 volumes (Box 38)
    - Jurisdictional Amount, 1 volumes (Box 38)
    - Jury Trials, 1 volumes (Box 38)
    - Kolene, 1 volumes (Box 38)
    - Mackinac Island Conference, 1 volumes (Box 38)
    - Manual for Criminal Tax Trials, 1 volumes (Box 38)
    - Miscellaneous Research, 1 volumes (Box 38)
    - Miscellaneous-Closed cases (Box 39)
    - Obscenity, 1 volumes (Box 39)
    - Pamphlet-"On Behalf of the People Justice Talbot Smith (Box 39)
    - Dissents" (Box 39)
    - Photostats Evidence, 1 volumes (Box 39)
    - Product Liability, 2 volumes (Box 39)
    - Proving Federal Crimes, 1 volumes (Box 39)
    - Restitution, 1 volumes (Box 39)
    - Selective Service, 3 volumes (Box 40)
    - Sentencing, 1 volumes (Box 40)
    - Shaw-Walker, 2 volumes (Box 40)
    - State-Federal Jurisdiction, 1 volumes (Box 40)
    - Stilson Tool Case, 1 volumes (Box 40)
    - Trials, 1 volumes (Box 41)
    - Trial Judges Journal, 1 volumes (Box 41)
    - Un-seaworthiness, 1 volumes (Box 41)
  - Alphabetical II
    - ABA Journal article material, 2 folders (Box 42)
    - Book material and speeches (Box 42)
    - Book material and speeches (Box 43)
    - Disability of Judges (Box 43)
    - Diversity, 2 folders (Box 43)
    - Edsel Griffin (Box 43)
    - Free Press-Fair Trial (Box 44)
    - Jury Instruction (Box 44)
    - Magistrate's Act (Box 44)
    - Mediation (Box 44)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 44)
    - Motions (Box 44)
    - Multi-district litigation (Box 44)
    - Narcotics Rehabilitation Act of 1966 (Box 44)
    - National Parole Aid (Box 44)
    - Naturalization (Box 44)
    - Neighborhood Legal Services Center (Box 44)
    - Norfolk Railroad (Box 44)
    - Notes pertaining to procedure (Box 44)
    - O'Connell, John T. (Box 44)
    - Old cases (Box 44)
    - Opinions-Attorney General (Box 44)
    - Opinions-publication (Box 44)
    - Other judges' opinions (Box 44)
    - Pictures (Box 44)
    - Probation matters (Box 44)
    - Proposed federal rules of appellate procedure (Box 44)
    - Proposed rules re forfeiture of collateral (Box 44)
    - Riots (Box 44)
    - Rubinoff, Charles (Box 44)
    - Rules-western district (Box 44)
    - School cases (Box 44)
    - Security of building (Box 44)
    - Sentencing Institute, 2 folders (Box 44)
    - Six man juries (Box 44)
    - Tax cases (Box 44)
    - Telephone Survey (Box 44)
    - Title VII (Box 44)
    - Tydings Committee (Box 45)
    - Tydings letters, 3 folders (Box 45)
    - Voir Dire (Box 45)
    - Wherry Act (Box 45)
    - Wiretapping (Box 45)
    - Wisconsin speeches and miscellaneous (Box 46)
- Other materials
  The Other materials series includes sound recordings, photographs, a large assortment of various honorary awards and achievements, and a scrapbook covering the years 1934 to 1976.
  - Sound recordings, 2 audiotapes reel-to-reel tapes; analog; 7 in.
    - Talbot Smith and George Edwards undated (Box 46)
    - Lieutenant Governor Phil Hart. Talbot Smith February 27, 1957 (Box 46)
  - Photographs (Box 46)
  - Photographs, Citations and Awards (Box 47)
  - Scrapbook 1934-1976 (Box 47)